

PHD CANDIDATE IN COMPUTER SCIENCE · RESEARCHER (SOFTWARE ENGINEERING-HCI

Fairfax, Virginia, USA

🗷 smhasanmansur@gmail.com | 🏕 smhasanmansur.netlify.app | 🖸 hasanmansur | 🛅 smhasanmansur | 🎓 S M Hasan Mansur

Summary_

Research focus: "Automated Software Engineering via Multimodal Machine Learning". Research Interests: Software Engineering, HCI, Machine Learning, Generative AI and Large Language Model (LLM). Publication track record in top-tier SWE venues. 5+ years of professional experience in developing scalable, distributed, and enterprise-grade products. Open to relocation and no sponsorship required.

Professional Experience

George Mason University

Virginia, USA

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2021 - Aug 2024

- · Areas of Contribution: Ethical Software Design, Software Evolution, Software Accessibility and Software Documentation.
- Currently leading a research project aimed toward developing a multimodal model (vision-code-comment) for code summarization.
- Designed and developed AidUI, an automated approach to detect and localize deceptive design patterns on UIs.
- · Co-contributor of MotorEase, an approach to detect motor-impairment accessibility violations in app UIs.
- · Co-contributor of GUIEvo, an approach to update UI code by detecting changes between existing and proposed designs.
- Collaborated in developing datasets to serve as benchmarks for Bug Reporting and Bug Localization.

George Mason University

Virginia, USA

GRADUATE TEACHING ASSISTANT

Aug 2024 - Current | Aug 2018 - May 2021

• Mentored students, graded assignments, and proctored exams. Courses: Python Programming, Database, Computer Vision, Formal Methods.

Ice9 Ltd. Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Apr 2017 - Jul 2018

- Member of the core engineering team responsible for the development and maintenance of SMASHBOARD.CO, a social CRM product.
- · Collaborated with the Technical Lead on strategic planning and decision-making for architecture design, development, testing and deployment.
- · Lead the development and integration of social media query management and analytics module for INSTAGRAM.
- · Optimized database and implemented master-replica architecture to resolve the sync delay of real time social queries.
- Collaborated in implementing the migration of the core product from Rackspace to AWS.

Synchronous ICT Dhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Feb 2015 - Apr 2017

- · Lead the team to develop user management, search and notification platforms of project COMX, an in-house application framework.
- Assessed the capacity to deliver, formed sprints and released duration based development milestones.

DcastaliaDhaka, Bangladesh

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Aug 2013 - Jan 2015

- Developed and published HE BUSINESS MANAGER, a native Android app for inventory management of healthcare products.
- · Collaborated with the backend team on requirements analysis, architecture design, development, testing and deployment.

Mercedes-Benz Group AG (former Daimler AG)

Ulm, Germany

STUDENT INTERN

Oct 2012 - Jul 2013

Developed a KVP (key-value pair) parser to convert the unstructured stream of environment perception data into a canonical form.

Grameenphone Ltd.

Dhaka, Bangladesh

System Engineer

Jul 2007 - Feb 2011

• Member of the transmission network configuration and optimization team to serve over 20 million mobile users.

Publications

- Arun Krishnavajjala, S M Hasan Mansur, Justin Jose, Kevin Moran, "MotorEase: Automated Detection of Motor Impairment Accessibility Issues in Mobile App Uls", ICSE'24
- Junayed Mahmud, Nadeeshan De Silva, Safwat Ali Khan, Seyed Hooman Mostafavi, **S M Hasan Mansur**, Oscar Chaparro, Andrian (Andi) Marcus, Kevin Moran, "On Using GUI Interaction Data to Improve Text Retrieval-based Bug Localization", ICSE'24
- Sabiha Salma, S M Hasan Mansur, Kevin Moran, Yule Zhang, "GUIEvo: Automated Evolution of Mobile Application GUIs from Mockups", MSR'24
- S M Hasan Mansur, Kevin Moran, "Toward Automated Tools to Support Ethical GUI Design", ICSE'23: Companion Proceedings
- S M Hasan Mansur, Sabiha Salma, Damilola Awofisayo, Kevin Moran, "AidUI: Toward Automated Recognition of Dark Patterns in User Interfaces", ICSE'23
- Tyler Wendland, Jingyang Sun, Junayed Mahmud, S M Hasan Mansur, Steven Huang, Kevin Moran, Julia Rubin, Mattia Fazzini, "AndroR2: A
 Dataset of Manually-Reproduced Bug Reports for Android apps", MSR'21

Tech Skills

Programming Python, Javascript, Java, C

Databases MySQL, MongoDB, Redis, Elasticsearch, SQLite **Libraries** OpenCV, NumPy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Socket.IO

ML/DL/NLP Transformer, LLM finetuning, PyTorch, Hugging Face, scikit-learn, spaCy

Backend/Cloud/DevOps Node.js, Express.js, REST API, AWS, Docker, Git

Selected Research

Multimodal Code Summarization

Ongoing

PRINCIPAL CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

- Goal: To investigate how visual information from UI impacts in automated code summarization.
- · Identified the research gap after conducting literature review of related works. Formulated the design of approach to address the gap.
- Developed the data extraction pipeline to collect and map multi-modal data (code, comment, UI) from open-source app repositories.
- Currently leading the team to conduct data exploratory analysis and labeling of the dataset.
- Currently developing a model that aims toward learning from multi-modal data for code summarization.

AidUI Published, ICSE'23

PRINCIPAL CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

paper link, project repo

- AidUI is an automated approach to detect and localize deceptive design patterns on UIs.
- Developed a unified taxonomy and a set of heuristic rules to detect visual-textual cues that signify the presence of deceptive UI design patterns.
- Automated the data pipeline to extract UIs from publicly available app usage videos and screenshots by prior studies.
- · Designed and developed an approach that leverages computer vision and NLP techniques to detect different deceptive patterns on UI.
- Implemented an automated evaluation pipeline. Dockerized and published research artifacts in a public repository.

MotorEase Published, ICSE'24

CO-CONTRIBUTOR | SAGE LAB, UCF

paper link, project repo

- MotorEase is an approach to detect motor-impairment accessibility violations in app UIs.
- Developed the initial prototype of the "Semantic Text Matching" component of the automated approach.
- Collaborated with the lead contributor on labeling and curation of the dataset.

Education _____

2018-25	George Mason University, PhD candidate in Computer Science	Virginia, USA
2023	George Mason University, MS in Computer Science	Virginia, USA
2007	Shah Jalal University of Science & Technology, BS in Computer Science	Bangladesh

Honors & Awards

2023	NSF Travel Award, ICSE'23	Australia
2022	Best Poster Presentation Award, GMU CS Research Symposium	Virginia, USA
2019	Summer Research Initiation Award, GMU CS Dept.	Virginia, USA

Selected Open Source Projects

2020	Ontorjat, implementation of DNS client & Distance vector Routing protocot.	ргојесттеро
2020	Drishtipat , Implementation of different concepts/topics of Computer Vision.	project repo
2017	Tasky , A backend boilerplate featuring Role Based Access Control, Searching, Token Authentication, TDD.	project repo

Professional Services

Innian DC Marchan MCD224

2024	Junior PC Member, MSR 24
2022	Co-Reviewer, MSR'22
2021-23	External Reviewer, ICSE'21, ICSE'23, SANER'22, SANER'23, ASE'22, MSR'21, ICPC'21

Volunteering_____

2022	Co-Mentor , Aspiring Scientists Summer Internship Program, GMU
2021-22	Director-Web Services , Bangladeshi Graduate Student Association, GMU
2002-07	Member, KIN, Humanitarian Organization, SUST, Bangladesh